Welcome to the 2026 release wave one
version of Business Central. This is the
launch edition and the video here you
are seeing here is about enhanced
finance analytics.
We invested in this
for three things: better reports, faster
reports, and in-client analysis of of
things related to finance.
Um
You see some some icons here. That means
that there are additional videos that
you can go and check out. But we're
we're in this video I'm going to talk
about added subtotals all the way down
to analysis tabs. And then the other two
here, go check out
related videos for enhanced financial
reporting and demo data.
In the fall of 2025, we
released a lot of Excel layouts for
existing reports. And it's For finance,
we did the three deferral reports for
GL, purchase, and sales.
We got some feedback that these reports
were missing subtotals. So here you can
see the version we shipped in the fall.
In in the pivot table, it there's no
subtotal totals. It's it's an easy
change. You can do it on your on your
own versions. But we're also shipping in
Business Central out of the box the
deferral reports
with subtotals included.
Another thing that actually the the
types of reports in in Business Central
that all started the Excel layouts wave
was back in version 25. And here the
what we shipped back then was a lot of
trial balance reports in finance and
some other things. Um those finance
reports were not fast. So
um we we took the time to actually
performance tune them from the trial
balance all the way down to trial
balance previous year.
Uh
and they run much faster.
Now, when we mess with finance reports,
we want to be a little bit careful. So,
therefore, we have put these new uh the
new
tuned reports under a feature management
flag for now. In case something uh you
you you find that they're not showing
the right numbers, we try to test as
much as we can. You can always go back
to the old behavior, at least for this
release wave and maybe the next one, but
if you want to take get the speed now,
just toggle this and you will have much
faster trial balance in Excel.
And finally, we added for finance
um in this release wave, it's possible
to ship analysis views out of the box
with the application, and therefore, we
are shipping some of these to the
finance area, specifically for GL
registered and fixed asset ledgers
pages. They now come with with out of
the box analysis views. These are
shipped in 20 eight  X, so they're
not in the April release yet, but they
will come very soon.
And if you want to see more examples of
things that you can do with analysis
mode in finance, go to Microsoft Learn
and find the ad hoc analysis of finance
data article. Here you see more examples
of what we ship. Uh some of these
examples require you to filter in on
certain accounts or things in your chart
of accounts. So, so these are not easy
for us to ship out of the box, but you
can create them very easily. Copy the
description of what to do into uh
Copilot analysis assist, and and it will
give you these additional uh reports or
analysis.
I also want to highlight or do a
commercial of enhanced financial
reporting session. So, go check the
link. There's ton of thing happening in
finance reporting. If you watch this on
financial analytics analytics, you
definitely want to see the things on
finance reporting as well.
And just a short bonus
related to to finance, we're adding new
demo data in fixed assets for
transactions data for acquisitions and
depreciations.
Because this come out of the box in a
demo company, you can do a lot better,
easier Well, you are able to demo all
the reports
that exist in in fixed assets at least
if they are in these two acquisitions
and depreciations. There's a full
session on demo data. If that's your
thing, go to the description and and and
see that as well.
Anything related to financial analytics
is described under
aka.ms/bcfinanceanalytics.
That's the landing page for everything
financial reporting, building reports,
Power BI, you name it. So, if you don't
know this resource, there's a gold mine
of examples and things where it can make
your finance life much easier.
And if you think that this is too much,
why not try the new copilot or in in
Microsoft Learn where you can get an AI
summary of any of these pages,
especially for the building finance
reports. There are a lot, so maybe have
an AI to summarize what's there and then
dive further in.
I mentioned the enhanced finance
reporting related session, so go
definitely check that out.
And other related sessions, if you're
interested in analytics
span from sales analytics all the way
down to enhanced demo data to mode.
Those links are also in the description
of this video. So uh so go check that
out as well.
After my goodbye, there is a a little
bit on general Business Central
resources. If you don't If you know them
already, uh here, skip this. If you
don't, uh stay tuned or or keep watching
the video. For now, financial analytics
uh is is over. This video is over. I
wish you a great day and uh see you in
another time. Bye.
We have compiled a number of general
resources that we believe are key both
for partners, but also uh Business
Central customers. Most Some of these
are partner. Some of them are also for
customers. So, the first one is
called aka.ms/bcall.
This is a partner resource for that
contains lists of every other aka link
that is needed for you to understand
anything about both the Business Central
product, but also processes around it.
We call these aka links because they're
called aka.ms and then for
forward/something. And with Business
Central links, we all always prefix with
BC and then something.
The next one is uh our uh partner
network uh social media for for Business
Central partners, Viva. Viva Engage. So,
aka.ms/bcvivaengage
is where you go and interact with other
partners. It's not open for customers.
So, this is where you can ask uh
questions, interact with the product
group, interact with you with with each
other
uh in a in a closed network.
Second link A third link is for both
partners and customers. We are called
office hours. So, office hours is
something we do once or twice a month
from the product group engaging with the
community about new features or things
we want to discuss. aka.ms/bcofficehours
is the is the place where you go to find
out about upcoming events. These are
recorded. I believe the recordings are
available only to partners, but the live
events are available to customers as
well.
Fourth link is YouTube, our YouTube
channel. I'll talk about that
in the next slide and LinkedIn in the
next slide. And then finally for for
Microsoft partners, the BC's
aka.ms/bcpartnerportal
is where you get
a lot of the resources as a partner such
as compete decks,
pitch decks, and a lot of other
resources.
For LinkedIn, this is our product
group's LinkedIn profile. We have 30k or
more followers, so both partners and
customers. This is the place where we
from the product group put in news and
small bits of information outside the
official channel. So, follow us
on LinkedIn to learn what's happening
right now
in in this in the around the product.
And then
also on our YouTube channel, this is
where you're probably watching this
aka.ms/bcyoutube.
We put in not only these launch editions
twice a year, but also copilot and AI
video shorts, tips and tricks, technical
deep dives, under the hood.
We even have this what's cooking where
we put little nuggets of of videos out
for new features that are even coming in
on the YouTube channel before they're
coming in the release notes. So, watch
and maybe bookmark us on YouTube. And
also notice all the playlists. So, that
all the content is also organized in
areas, not only all the videos. So, if
you have an area that's has special
interest such as analytics,
um you can find an
a playlist and kind of see all the
content related to that.
And that's it. That is truly it. We
won't
There will be no more. So, thank you for
watching all the way to the end. And
again, have a great day. Thank you.